Guide to the Vassar College Training Camp for Nurses Records, 1917-1999 (bulk 1918-1919)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Vassar College Training Camp for Nurses Records
1917-1999
1918-1919
Vassar College. Training Camp for Nurses
1.0 cubic foot (3 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Materials relating to Vassar College's Training Camp for Nurses, a program initiated to supply much-needed nurses for World War I.
Administrative History
The Vassar College Training Camp for Nurses was the result of a Vassar Alumnae Association request to have the college campus used to aid the war effort during the summer of 1918. A committee was formed to investigate various options, and in the end the nursing program was chosen because it targeted college women and would provide them with skills of continued use after the war. The program was endorsed by the Council of National Defense (CND), the Red Cross, as well as several hospitals. The CND appointed a committee of medical educators to formulate the curriculum. Members included Isabel M. Stewart (Columbia University), Elizabeth Burgess (New York State Inspector of Training Schools), and Annie Strong (Simmons College). Recruiting, fund-raising and publicity responsibilities were handed to a group of alumnae which included Ada Thurston, Mabel Kirk and Minnie Blodgett. Vassar undergraduates contributed as well by volunteering at the farm and dairy in order to feed the participants. The program itself was an intensive 3-month series of courses followed by another year of practical training at the affiliated hospitals.
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, news clippings, reports, printed material and photographs relating to Vassar College's Training Camp for Nurses.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Clappison, Gladys Bonner. Vassar's Rainbow Division, 1918. [S.l.: s.n.], c1964. [Available in both the Main Library and Grille: LD7182.9 .C42 1964]
MacCracken, Henry Noble. "Girls Who Want to Go to France," Independent, 24 (11 May 1918): 248, 258 [Main Library AP2 .I53]
"Mobilizing Women as Nurses," Literary Digest, 57 (27 Apr 1918): 33 [Main Library AP2 .L58]
The Thermometer (a publication of Vassar Farm Unit and the Training Camp for Nurses) [Grille Dewey Folio 378.7V Z5 and Folio 378.7V Z52]
Henry Noble MacCracken Papers, Folders 67.43-67.46
Subject Headings
Names:
Blodgett, Minnie Cumnock; Stewart, Isabel Maitland; Stimson, Marjorie; Thurston, Ada
Organizations:
Vassar College--Alumni and alumnae
Subjects:
Nursing--Study and teaching--New York (State); Women and war--United States; World War, 1914-1918--War work
VCL Categories
Vassar College Special Programs and Projects
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, January 2009.
Acquisition Information
This collection includes gifts from a number of donors, including Marjorie Mercer Kendig. Other materials were transfered from Vassar College offices, and some materials were collected by staff of the Vassar College Libraries.
Series List
- Series I. General Correspondence
- Series II. Clappison Correspondence >
- Series III. Speeches And Presentations
- Series IV. Course Material
- Series V. Articles and Clippings
- Series VI. Printed Material
- Series VII. Lists
- Series VIII. Miscellaneous
- Series IX. Photographs
Container List
- General Correspondence
  - Dec 1917 - Jan 1918 (Folder 1.1)
  - Feb 1918 (Folder 1.2)
  - March 1918 (Folder 1.3)
  - Apr - June1918 (Folder 1.4)
  - ca. 1918 (Folder 1.5)
  - 1920-1928 (Folder 1.6)
  - 1936, n.d. (Folder 1.7)
- Clappison Correspondence
  - 1959 -1961 (Folder 1.8)
  - 1962 - 1964, n.d. (Folder 1.9)
- Speeches And Presentations
  - "Newer Phases of Nursing Education,", n.d. (Folder 1.10)
  - [Presentation of the Vassar Plan], (2 copies with notes) (Folder 1.11)
  - Address to graduates by Herbert E. Mills (Folder 1.12)
  - Unidentified speech, possibly by Minnie Cumnock Blodgett (Folder 1.13)
- Course Material
  - Marjorie Mercer Kendig's notebooks, 1918 (Folders 1.14-1.15)
  - Marjorie Mercer Kendig's certificate, 1918 (Folder 1.16)
  - E.M. Buter's bibliography, 1918 (Folder 1.17)
  - I.M. Stewart's bibliography, 1918 (Folder 1.18)
  - Lists of textbooks (Folder 1.19)
  - Printed material (Folder 1.20)
- Articles and Clippings
  - Articles, 1918 (Folder 2.1)
  - Articles, 1919-1954 (Folder 2.2)
  - Clippings, ca. 1918-1919 (Folder 2.3)
  - Clippings, 1934-1999 (Folder 2.4)
  - Scrapbook of clippings, 1918 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook of clippings, reports and pamphlets, 1918 (Box 3)
- Printed Material
  - Poster announcing the Training Camp, 1918 (Box 3)
  - Vassar College Bulletins, 1918-1919 (Folder 2.5)
  - Nutting, M Adelaide - "Apprenticeship to Duty" (Folder 2.6)
  - Stewart, Isabel - "Nursing a National Service" (Folder 2.6)
  - Stewart, Isabel - "Preparatory Courses for Nurses" (Folder 2.6)
  - "The Work of the American Red Cross" (Folder 2.7)
  - "Opportunities in the Field of Nursing" (Folder 2.7)
  - "The Nations Calll for Nurses" (Folder 2.7)
  - Miscellaneous programs, notices and forms (Folders 2.8-2.9)
- Lists
  - Analysis of Registered Students, Colleges Represented at the Training Camp (Folder 2.10)
  - Those who attended the Training Camp for Nurses (Folder 2.11)
  - People who received applications, etc. (Folder 2.12)
  - Colleges addressed by speakers (Folder 2.13)
  - Cooperating Hospitals (Folder 2.14)
  - Organizers (Folder 2.15)
  - Speakers (Folder 2.16)
  - Bibliography of material about the Training Camp (Folder 2.17)
- Miscellaneous
  - Vassar Board of Trustees resolution (Folder 2.18)
  - Mills Gate (Folder 2.19)
  - The Thermometer material, 1918-1921 (Folder 2.20)
  - Notes and receipts (Folder 2.21)
  - Marjorie Stimson materials, approximately 1918-1934; (correspondence, printed material, photographs) (Folder 2.23)
  - Reunion booklet, May 1965 (Box 3)
- Photographs
  - Photographs (Folder 2.22)